senso intorno ad ipotesi di questo tipo e quindi è un semestre e una sfida difficile per
il nostro Paese. Oggi quindi la nostra conferenza inizia con questo tema prioritario, la Costituzione.
Domani invece dedicheremo i nostri lavori alla politica estera, che è un altro tema
fondamentale e divideremo i lavori in gruppi sui Balcani, sul Mediterraneo, sulla Russia,
sull'Iraq, che sono punti di grande interesse per l'Italia e per l'Unione Europea, ma che
sono anche legati strettamente alla richiesta di riforma della Costituzione, e cioè in
altre parole al rafforzamento di quel ruolo di politica estera e di sicurezza che è necessario
perché l'Unione Europea giochi un ruolo importante internazionale. Quindi diciamo che queste due
parti della nostra conferenza sono legate a filo doppio proprio per la logica con cui
si tengono assieme una riforma istituzionale che di fatto crea questa capacità europea
di agire come attore internazionale. Ecco, di fronte con queste considerazioni, io volei
naturalmente ringraziare anche gli sponsor di questa nostra iniziativa, la Commissione
di Bruxelles, la Compagnia di San Paolo, ma soprattutto il Ministero degli Esteri, che
ci ha seguito molto, è qui rappresentato fra il resto da Ferdinando Nelli-Feroci, con cui
abbiamo confezionato, diciamo, questa conferenza. E un grazie anche al circolo ufficiali, Palazzo
Barberini, che ci ha ospitato per il calore con cui ci ha accolto, proprio in merito mi
è tolto le parole. Grazie e passo la parola in ordine alfabetico, seguiamo, ma anche
in ordine siccome gerarchico, perché come vicepresidente della Convenzione chiederei
a Giuliano Matto di aprire la discussione. Grazie.
Quanti minuti? 19 minuti. Ok, well, substantially Gianni, you said what has to be said. It's
not perfect, the draft that we have produced is not perfect. I wonder if the Intergovernmental
Conference is equipped to improve it or to worsen it. And I frankly think that they might
more easily worsen it than improve it, which means that the shortcomings of the existing
text are doomed to remain in my view. I'm very pessimistic on this, because I sound
and their positions of national governments ready to do something in terms of changing
what has been done and what they have in mind to change is on the wrong side. Of course,
worsening or improving depends on what you think. Let's say in my view, in my view I'm
firmly convinced to pick one point that giving each of our member states a commissioner with
full rights is not an improvement. I understand that the commission, for reasons that frankly
I don't share, has a different position. But in my view, in my view, there is a limit
to the efficiency of the commission that doesn't go beyond a certain number of commissioners
holding a portfolio without slicing the existing portfolios into pieces that requires the commission
not to go beyond something that is around 15 full members. And this was exactly what
not Giscard but Jacques Delors advised us to do. Now, let me state this point. In our
view, let's say human beings may be part of the structure. Only 15 full members of it,
but other commissioners coming from other countries can be appointed and can be useful
as long as they are something such as delegated commissioners. When people say, well, there
are so many national governments with 30, 40 ministers, the French government is quoted
as a government having 40 ministers, but at this point any French who knows how things
are in his or her country objects, but only 15 are full ministers, the other are delegated
ministers. And this is what we expect the commission to be. Consider that initially
we called, we named the other commissioners, delegated commissioners. I made a negotiation
with the national governments in the convention. They accepted, they accepted all of them,
all of them, 15 full members on a strictly equal rotation basis. At that point they
asked me to give the others a name that they could sell in their countries. And it was
not a matter of selling, not a matter of substance. And they objected to the delegated commissioner
because it seemed something more hierarchically subordinated than something else. And therefore
at the end we called the first class commissioners European commissioners and the other ones
commissioners. At this point there are reactions in some countries and they say, but what
are these gentlemen going to do hanging around? They are not even delegated to do something.
Now the response is read the draft and the draft says that the president of the commission
is responsible toward the European Parliament for the activities of these commissioners,
which means that the president will give them missions to each of them and he or she
will be responsible for their activities toward the parliament. It is, I must say at the end
of the story, the same kind of commission that the commission had in mind, the two tiers
commission, which means that in a two tiers commission not necessarily all of them have
the voting rights around. Now this is a crucial point in my view. I am convinced that with
the commission having at the end of the story more than 30 full members with voting rights
the commission would become an intergovernmental arena, somehow reducing its potential as the
necessary engine in the European interest. For several member states changing the draft
in this sense would be improving it. So we have to be very clear on what we consider improving
or worsening. I can expect this kind of thing to have quite a significant pressure during
the intergovernmental conference, which would be a pity because the commission has been
strengthened throughout the process. I must say I am one of those who have always thought
that a long term president is useful for the council. So let's say Herman is one that
was opposing it and wanted the prize for it. So if I have to swallow the president, this
is Herman's argument, what do you give me? And he got something because he got for the
commission significant improvement in terms of tasks, not just the monopoly in legislative
initiative, not just the almost monopoly in executive functions, but also the yearly
and multi yearly planning of union activities which is going to be organized on the basis
of the commission initiative, plus the European council meetings jointly prepared by the general
affairs council and by the commission, plus at the end the president of the commission
jointly with the president of the council supervising the preparation of the European
council and also the elimination of that clause by which there was an incompatibility between
the presidency of the European council and the presidency of the commission, which is
much less than the clause some of us had in mind to give the union a single president
in let's say 10 years, but at least it opens the way to it. Therefore the commission is
somehow safe in its role and the institutional balance has been preserved, but should the
arena I was envisaging this in my view would be a significant worsening in the future of
the institutional balance itself. Qualified majority, I don't think the IGC will do something
to widen the cases of qualified majority indeed. I don't think the IGC will do something to
widen the cases of qualified majority. At the end of the story there are some cases,
substantially some cases and you have several governments playing against here or there.
Taxation distorting competition could be somehow decided upon by qualified majority
voting, but you don't have the UK only, you also have Denmark, you also have Ireland,
you also have Sweden, you also have others. Social policies, it's not the UK, it's Germany
that is firmly opposing qualified majority in relation to the now Article 137 and they
don't want to go beyond Nice. France is already resenting the limited ventilation
that we introduced in agricultural policy, giving something to legislation and much more
to Council's regulations. I have already seen amendments that reduce the something given
to European legislation and should this amendment be accepted sooner or later, legislation
would just have the smoke and all of the meat would be and would remain for Council's regulation.
What can I expect from the IGC that France drops its objections to widening the role
of qualified majority and co-decision in agricultural policy in exchange for Germany widening
the area of social policies that go to co-decision and qualified majority? This is something
unpredictable and therefore to conclude with, I don't think that there will be leftovers
formally, I am convinced that there will be leftovers substantially, so I don't expect
the IGC to formally decide that unsettled issue will go to a further appointment with
either a Convention or an IGC. I expect them to remain where we have remained if not
worse in this area. I include in this area also amendments of the text because you are
right Gianni, it would be so reasonable and this was something that Herman and I proposed
jointly, we accept unanimity for any amendment that imply further transfers of sovereignty
from member states to the Union, while any other amendment which simply implies reorganisation
at the European level of existing competences and therefore does not reduce or touch upon
what remains in the hands of member states, why shouldn't this be approved by a majority
vote? Possibly by a super qualified majority voting, what's the reason? Really there is
no reason, I ignore now the fact that they want the procedure of international treaties
to apply also for the future therefore not the European Council but the IGC, not the
national parliaments approving but the national parliaments ratifying which is really something
that for me as a lawyer means treaty, cannot mean constitution but independently also of
it, why don't they accept majority voting when their remaining competences are not
touched upon by the amendments? The funny thing is that at the end of this process,
this one, we might find ourselves with an overall more cumbersome procedure for amendments
than the existing one because nowadays we have several clauses that can be modified
by quasi autonomous or autonomous procedures and as we say in technical jargon by which
national parliaments are not involved, unanimity is necessary anyway but the unanimity of
the European Council could be enough now to change several clauses of the existing
treaties. Paradoxically you understand how times change, one of the clauses that can
be changed only by decision of the European Council without involving national parliaments
is the clause on the number of commissioners that has become the hottest issue of the European
Council of all, so I don't expect this to change, what do I expect? I do expect in
a few years the union to face some deep crisis because they cannot decide on the basis of
unanimity. Assuming unanimity as the method for their decisions, the European Council
simply means that they cannot decide even more in an enlarged Europe and therefore after
a while they will realize perhaps by themselves that if they really want to exercise the competencies
they wanted at the European level but unanimously decided upon, they will have to change. In
the last three months of the convention this was not even mentioned anymore by national
parliaments because it was thought that this was a positive result which will help us
in the future to come to a good relationship between national parliaments and European
parliaments in order to fulfill our responsibility to control the executive branches. Thank you
very much. Thank you, Elmer Brock, for your evaluation of the result of the convention
and also for your sharp judgment on the role of the IGC. In any case, may I now, before
addressing to the audience and ask for some questions or comments, may I ask Ferdinando
Nell'Efferoci to comment about this first round of introductions without anticipating
the priorities of the Italian presidencies which will be part of the next session. Thank
you. Gianni, thank you. I think I can limit my remarks to very brief ones because I'd
like to say a little more on how we would like to proceed in the preparation of the
IGC and in the conduct of the IGC in fact. Broadly speaking, I'd like to confirm what
has already been said at official level by several representatives of the Italian government
including Vice President Fini who has been an active member of the convention, including
Presidente Berlusconi, including Foreign Minister Mr. Flattini, and this is to confirm
that we really very much appreciate the results achieved by the convention. We think that
we are in the presence of a historical development. If we look back into the past way of proceeding
in treaty reforms and treaty revisions, we are now faced with an extraordinary crisis
of innovation and we are also very much satisfied with the overall articulation of the draft
constitutional treaty which has been submitted to the government in Tessaloniki. Maybe as
many others, members of parliaments, representatives of governments, we would have had preferences
here and there. There would have been solutions that we would like to see more than others
reflected in the draft treaty, but as a whole we consider that it's a very good basis
for the work of the intergovernmental conference. I fully share the appreciation which was made
a few minutes ago by Presidente Amato when he noted that there is a risk in reopening
the carefully balanced text of the treaty dispositions and the risk is that we may
fall backwards more than move forwards. We would carefully study all the alternatives
that we will be faced with when launching the IGC, but certainly we will carefully
have in mind this note of caution. In more general terms, I think that I fully share
the individual points that were made by President Brock and that all together we share his
points of appreciation for the text. But having said that, I think I would prefer to leave
it for my next intervention, some more detailed remarks on how we intend to proceed further
on on our way towards the organization of the intergovernmental conference. Thank you,
Alvaro. Ok, thank you very much. Now I address to the audience for questions and comments.
Of course there is a mobile phone. Yes, please, could you come here? Alvaro de Vasconcelos
from the Instituto de Estudios Strategicos of Lisbon. Yes, thank you very much. I want
to make a comment and put a question to the panel. The comment is that I have the feeling
that there was real progress in making the European integration more democratic, more
transparent, more close to the citizens. Let's say if you look from outside, in Europe we
are better now. Integration is moving forward. My question is the following. If this is true
for Europe, it's not the same thing in relation to the ability of the European Union to project
its values in the international scene. It's clear about what you said, but also just reading
the constitution, that even the premise that came from the convention are not in this text.
We have no majority voting as it was proposed in the Franco-German proposal. On the fence
there is not really great progress. We don't have a clause of solidarity, clear clause
of solidarity. So we have not really progressed on the ability to act internationally. So
now coming to the question, is this the lessons you took from the Iraqi crisis? You spoke
as a parliamentarian, I spoke as a citizen. And looking to your work, I ask myself, have
you done your work based on the Iraqi crisis to make the European Union more able to act
internationally? Or it was just the opposite, that the Iraq crisis made you more timid,
less able to make the reform that was asked? Because looking to the debate in the convention
and the result, it seems that there is two moments. Before the Iraq crisis, things seemed
to go forward on the foreign policy and defense. And after the Iraq crisis, to opposite to
the Iraq crisis, we have no lessons of Europeans in the streets that ask for more Europe in
the demonstrations all over Europe. We don't have that. More Europe in international affairs.
And it's a demand from outside Europe too. It's not only in Europe. If we go to North
Africa, to the Middle East, to Latin America, to Africa, people say we need more Europe,
not less Europe in the international arena. Why it is not there?
Thank you. May I suggest to collect some questions and comments and then go back to the panel?
I have another person there. Can you introduce yourself, please?
My name is Rafał Trzaskowski. I'm from the European Center in Poland and I have a question
to Mr. Edmund Brock. You have said that what parliamentarians achieved shouldn't change,
have no right to change, and it's very difficult to disagree with that statement. But wouldn't
you agree that hadn't there been an IGC plan, the achievements of the convention wouldn't
be so far reaching? In other words, if you talk to many of the participants of the convention,
parliamentarians included, some of them are not satisfied with the draft treaty. And
so it seems that some of them have adopted a strategy, let's not spoil the celebration
and let's wait for the IGC to change certain things that we don't like. You have said
that there will be no big changes during the IGC. What changes do you envisage, if any?
Thank you.
Thank you. Other questions? We have a very timid audience here, not the convention, but
the audience. Please. Yes, please.
Dominik Hanf from the College of Europe in Bruges. This one?
Yeah, okay.
My question is concerning the adoption of the new constitution. All these matters on the
adoption and the later revision of the constitution by a qualified majority have not really been
discussed, but there will be a problem of fact that what will happen if one or two or three
member states will not adopt the new constitution. So I know that the treaty, or the draft
treaty, will have a problem and take political consequences, but my question is what will
be the political consequences?
Okay, thank you. Another question here and then there.
The question is the following.
Your name, please, to introduce yourself.
Sorry, my name is Jan Willems. I'm the Belgian ambassador to the Quid Inan here in Rome.
Why did the convention not suggest to the IGC that the end result, the constitution,
would enter into force with less than a new unanimous ratification in the different member
states? Because we can face the result and the risk is greater that one country would
block the entry into force of this new constitution, which would be tragic.
Thank you very much, Ambassador. Another question there.
My name is Brendan Donnelly from the Federal Trust in London. Can I put a question arising
from what Elmar Brock said about foreign policy, but I'd like comments if I may from everyone
on that subject. Elmar Brock spoke as if the most important reason why a relatively cautious
text on the question of foreign policy emerged was British opposition. It's widely believed
in the United Kingdom, and I'd like a comment on this if I may, that while the British government
is the most outspoken in its opposition to a more daring approach to foreign policy,
in fact at least the French government and in some moods the German government has more
sympathy with that view than is always publicly said. Now, whether that's right or wrong,
can I just make the further point that British public and probably British elite opinion will
never be convinced of any different proposition until what Elmar said was a possibility does
happen. If you want to convince the British that they're the only people who are standing
in the way of a more bold foreign policy, then it's up to others to take the lead.
Other questions? Yes, please.
General Pozzi, retired from the Italian Army, member of the Istituto D'Affari Internazionali.
What about the security and defense? What will be the provisions in that sector? I would
like to know if it is, of course, is in the agenda, but what ideas are going to be in
the agenda that will be constructed in the end? Thank you.
Thank you. Other questions? Questions can be also addressed in Italian.
I'm Paolo Calzini of Milano University. How do you assess the fact that there has been
so little debate and participation in terms of public opinion in Europe around the question
of the Constitution? Thank you.
Okay. I would suggest to go back to the two main speakers and ask them to answer or to
comment or to conclude their reasoning here by thanking them, of course, for their patience
and having succeeded to resist this hot climate. Please.
Well, first of all, when you say that public opinion was somehow far from the Convention,
you say something that is only partially true and much less than you think. First, you
have to compare the attention given by public opinion to the Convention with the attention
given to IGCs, because this is the only alternative, the benchmark. For the first time, if you
look at this from this angle, we had an enormous debate compared with the past, a transparent
debate that we never had in the past on modifications of the treaties. Please give a look at the
side of the Convention and give a look at that part of the side that is named Forum.
Under Forum, you have all the associations, groups and centers of research and others
that took part in the debate by sending contribution, by interacting with us, by taking part in
meetings, because we also had meetings with the representatives of this group. They are
hundreds and hundreds, and not just the traditional lobbies that are based in Brussels and that
of course show up whatever happens in Brussels, but also associations and groups from all
the existing member states and the new member states. Some of them, unbelievable, because
I did never expect the association for the safeguard of the right to nudity to have something
to suggest, which if they suggested something, nothing appeared in the text, I suppose, except
I hope the Charter takes care also of nudity, I don't know. But anyhow, there was quite
an attention, so please don't say as usual, well, the citizens were absent. This is not
correct. I don't expect the attention of let's say millions and millions of people to go
to an event such as the Convention. I expect those citizens who tend to be active to have
an opportunity to interact, to have a sense of responsibility, to have a sense of responsibility